Charles Evan Hughes Letters
Charles Evan Hughes Letters
1894-1934
Hughes, Charles Evans, 1862-1948.
67 items (SC)
Papers of the Lawyer, New York State governor, presidential candidate, U.S. Secretary of State. Outgoing correspondence, with the exception of two incoming letters from Horatio C. King and George B. McClellan. Most of the letters are responses to recommendations for various appointments and speaking invitations. Letters to John Barrett, Marthe Bibesco, Joseph Buffington, Samuel P. Cadman, Samuel M. Cavert, Edward Fallows, Bert M. Fernald, Roy G. Fitzgerald, Julius Frank, Robert H. Fuller, Martin H. Glynn, Paul Hickok, Hamilton Holt, R. U. Johnson, Winfield Jones, William A. Nash, Clarence Owens, Robert Paine, Amasa J. Parker, George Pratt, Palmer Ricketts, E. Quincy Smith, Robert E. Speer, Frederic J. Stimson, Charles Vrooman, Albert H. Walker, Henry Wallace, George W. Wickersham, and Sidney Woodward.
149385
Biographical History
Charles Evan Hughes (1862-1948) was an American lawyer and politician who served as Governor of New York, U.S. Secretary of State, and Chief Justice of the Supreme Court.
Charles Evan Hughes was born in Glen Falls, New York on April 11, 1862. His parents David Charles Hughes, a Methodist preacher, and Mary Connelly, a Baptist minister's daughter, were deeply religious. An intelligent child, Hughes began attending Madison College (presently Colgate University) at the age of fourteen before transferring to Brown University. He graduated first in his class from Columbia Law School and began practicing law in 1884. While working at the firm Chamberlin, Carter, and Hornblower, Hughes met his future wife, Antoinette Carter, the daughter of Walter S. Carter, a senior partner in the firm.
Hughes established himself politically by leading investigations into corporate corruption and the insurance industry. In 1906 he was elected Governor of New York. Four years later, President William Howard Taft appointed Hughes to the United States Supreme Court. Hughes left his Associate Justice position to run on the Republican nomination for President of the United States in 1916, but lost to Woodrow Wilson. After a few years in private practice, Hughes served as Secretary of State from 1921 to 1925 under Presidents Warren G. Harding and Calvin Coolidge. During his tenure, Hughes focused on various international efforts to avert another great war.
In 1930, President Herbert Hoover named Hughes the eleventh Chief Justice of the Supreme Court. The Hughes court faced the Great Depression and President Franklin D. Roosevelt's court-packing plan. While in this position Hughes also oversaw the opening of the Supreme Court building in 1935. He resigned his post in 1941. Hughes died in Cape Cod, Massachusetts on August 27, 1948.
Works Written by Hughes
1909 Conditions of Progress in the Democratic Government
1925 The Pathway of Peace, and Other Addresses
1927 The Supreme Court of the United States
1928 Our Relation with the Nations of the Western Hemisphere
1929 Pan American Peace Plans
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Charles Evan Hughes Letters are a collection of 65 outgoing and two incoming items written between 1894 and 1934. As a lawyer, New York State Governor, Secretary of State under Warren G. Harding, and Chief Justice of the U.S. Supreme Court, Hughes answered letters from constituents, politicians (Martin H. Glynn, George B. McClellan), editors (Hamilton Holt, Louis Wiley), and clergymen (S. Parkes Cadman, Samuel Cavert, Smith T. Ford, Paul Hickok, Charles MacFarland, Robert E. Speer). Most of the letters are responses to recommendations for various appointments (Joseph Buffington, Joseph Carlino, Edward H. Fallows, McClellan, Wiley) as well as social and speaking invitations (G. Lennox Curtis, Ford, D. W. Hakes, Roy F. Fitzgerald, Winfield Jones, Mrs. J. E. Norcross, Clarence J. Owens, Amasa Parker, D. H. Pierson, Palmer C. Ricketts). In addition to a number of letters of introduction (Marthe Bibesco, Diplomatic and Consular Office), there are also several responses to congratulatory messages received upon Lodge's assumption of various appointments (John Barrett, Ford, Lilla Day Monroe, William R. Rose).
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection contains one series, Correspondence, which is arranged chronologically. There is also an alphabetical Index to the Correspondence located at the end of the finding aid.
Subject and Genre Headings
New York State; Politics, government and public administration; Barrett, John, 1866-1938.; Bibesco, Marthe, ca. 1887-1973.; Buffington, Joseph, 1855-1947.; Cadman, S. Parkes (Samuel Parkes), 1864-1936.; Cavert, Samuel McCrea, 1888-1976.; Fallows, Edward Huntington, 1865-; Fernald, Bert M., 1858-1926.; Fitzgerald, Roy Gerald, 1875-1962.; Frank, Julius.; Fuller, Robert H. (Robert Higginson), 1865-1927.; Glynn, Martin Henry, 1871-1924.; Hickok, Paul Robinson, 1877-1945.; Holt, Hamilton, 1872-1951.; Hughes, Charles Evans, 1862-1948.; Johnson, Robert Underwood, 1853-1937.; Jones, Winfield, 1874-; King, Horatio C. (Horatio Collins), 1837-1918.; McClellan, George B. (George Brinton), 1865-1940.; Nash, William Alexander, 1840-1922.; Owens, Clarence J. (Clarence Julian).; Paine, Robert Treat, 1835-1910.; Parker, Amasa J. (Amasa Junius), 1807-1890.; Pratt, George Dupont, 1869-; Ricketts, Palmer C. (Palmer Chamberlain), 1856-1934.; Smith, E. Quincy (Edward Quincy), b. 1868.; Speer, Robert E. (Robert Elliott), 1867-1947.; Stimson, Frederic Jesup, 1855-1943.; Vrooman, Charles Elliott.; Walker, Albert Henry, 1844-1915.; Wallace, Henry Cantwell, 1866-1924.; Wickersham, George W. (George Woodward), 1858-1936.; Woodward, Sidney C.; Governors, New York (State); Politicians, United States.; New York (State), Politics and government, 1865-1950.; Letters.; Governors.; Politicians.
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions on this material
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - 1894-1907, 9 letters (Sc 79)
  - 1908, 7 letters (Sc 79)
  - 1909-1910, 6 letters (Sc 79)
  - 1911-1920, 8 letters (Sc 79)
  - 1921, 7 letters (Sc 79)
  - 1922, 5 letters (Sc 79)
  - 1923, 9 letters (Sc 79)
  - 1924-1925, 6 letters (Sc 79)
  - 1927-1928, 5 letters (Sc 79)
  - 1929-1930, 1934, 5 letters (Sc 79)
- Index to the Correspondence
  Bannard, Otto T.
  08 Apr 1908
  Barrett, John
  10 Jun 1921
  02 Mar 1925
  02 Nov 1927
  Bibesco, Marthe
  02 Dec 1921
  Blake, Irving
  08 May 1924
  Buffington, Joseph
  31 Mar 1921
  Cadman, Samuel Parkes
  09 Nov 1928
  Carlino, Joseph
  05 Dec 1906
  Cavert, Samuel McCrea
  31 May 1923
  Curtis, G. Lennox
  20 Dec 1911
  Diplomatic and Consular Officers
  24 May 1922
  09 Jun 1923
  15 Jun 1923
  Fallows, Edward Huntington
  04 Dec 1906
  Fernald, Bert M.
  24 Nov 1922
  Fishel, Henry W.
  25 Jun 1906
  Fitzgerald, Roy Gerald
  30 Nov 1916
  19 Jan 1925
  Ford, Smith T.
  01 Dec 1906
  27 Feb 1908
  23 Nov 1908
  25 Sep 1922
  Frank, Julius
  05 Mar? 1907
  04 Oct 1921
  08 May 1928
  26 Nov 1928
  Fuller, Robert Higginson
  19 Aug 1910
  Glynn, Martin H.
  10 Mar 1914
  Hakes, D. W.
  06 Feb 1908
  Henderson, Olive
  15 Aug 1923
  Hendrian, Otto A. (Mrs.)
  11 Jul 1924
  Hickok, Paul Robinson
  21 Mar 1921
  16 Apr 1923
  19 Feb 1925
  Holt, Hamilton
  12 Jan 1908
  Johnson, Robert Underwood
  12 Jan 1923
  Jones, Winfield
  07 Nov 1922
  King, Horatio Collins (incoming)
  04 Oct 1910
  McClellan, George B. (incoming)
  17 Apr 1907
  MacFarland, Charles S.
  04 Nov 1921
  Mason, C. E.
  15 Apr 1910
  Mendheim, Jesse M.
  12 Apr 1934
  Monroe, Lilla Day
  23 Jan 1925
  Morgan, Douglas O.
  13 Mar 1929
  Nash, William A.
  02 Sep 1907
  Norcross, J. E. (Mrs.)
  11 Jan 1908
  Owens, Clarence J.
  04 May 1923
  Paine, Robert Treat
  17 Dec 1894
  Parker, Amasa J.
  01 Mar 1917
  Pierson, D. H.
  29 May 1906
  Pratt, George Dupont
  18 Sep 1918
  Ricketts, Palmer Chamberlain
  24 Jan 1908
  Robinson, David
  02 Apr 1927
  Rose, William R.
  08 Mar 1921
  Smith, Edward Quincy
  01 Mar 1930
  Speer, Robert Elliott
  01 Oct 1923
  Stimson, Frederic Jesup
  02 Apr 1910
  Vrooman, Charles Elliott
  06 Nov 1915
  Walker, Albert Henry
  27 Nov 1909
  Wallace, Henry Cantwell
  17 Jan 1922
  Wickersham, George Woodward
  07 Dec 1929
  Wiley, Louis
  14 Dec 1929
  Woodward, Sidney C.
  07 Sep 1910
  Young, Benjamin Loring
  20 Nov 1919
  23 Nov 1919